A Guide to the Magruder Family Letters, 1859-1863
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Magruder Family Letters, 1859-1863
Library of Virginia
21243
74 leaves, negative photostats
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Mrs. J. D. Micks, Orange, Virginia, in 1938.
Biographical Information
Benjamin Henry Magruder (1808-1885) of Glenmore in Albemarle County, Virginia, married Maria Louisa Minor 15 December 1836, and they had several children including Julia Virginia Magruder (1837-1873) who married George Tyler (1817-1889) of Caroline County, Virginia; John Bowie Magruder, Eva M. Magruder who married E. H. DeJarnette of Caroline County, and Henry Minor Magruder (1845-1891). John Bowie Magruder was born 24 November 1839. He attended the University of Virginia, and was a teacher in Culpeper County, Virginia, when the Civil War began. He was a captain in the 57th Virginia Infantry, and was promoted to colonel before his death from wounds received at the battle of Gettysburg on 3 July 1863. James Watson Magruder, a cousin, was born 2 February 1839. He attended the University of Virginia in 1857-1858. A merchant in Fluvanna County, Virginia, when the Civil War began, he enlisted in Company K, 2nd Virginia Cavalry. A lieutenant, he was killed leading his company at Meadow Bridge, Virginia, 12 May 1864. Another cousin George Shelton Magruder was born 25 September 1842, and was a student when the Civil War began. He enlisted in the 13th Virginia Infantry and was wounded at the battle of Gaines Mill. George Shelton Magruder was cited for distinguished service at Fredericksburg in May 1863. He was killed in battle at Winchester, Virginia, 19 September 1864.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1859-1863, of the Magruder family of Albemarle and Fluvanna Counties, Virginia, consisting of letters, 1859-1863, from John Bowie Magruder (1839-1863) to his brother, Henry Minor Magruder (1845- 1891), commenting on family matters, business, education, and details of the campaigns John Magruder participated in; a letter, 20 December 1862, from John Magruder to his father Benjamin Henry Magruder discussing military actions and describing the battle of Fredericksburg; letter, 9 March 1862, from John Bowie Magruder to Evy [Eva] M. Magruder describing Fort Dillard and the surrounding Gates County, North Carolina, countryside; letter, 27 May 1863, from John Bowie Magruder to Julia Magruder Tyler commenting on a fight his command was in, its march to Richmond, Virginia, and plans for a Pennsylvania invasion; and letters, 1861-1863, from Henry Minor Magruder to John Bowie Magruder discussing business, family and personal matters. Also included are biographical notes on members of the Magruder family, including E. J. Magruder, George Shelton Magruder, John Hillery Magruder, James Watson Magruder, and E. T. H. Warren.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologicallly.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Magruder Family Letters, 1856-1865. Accession 21150. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
Contents List
- Letter, 14 August 1859, from John Bowie Magruder to Henry Minor Magruder discussing family news and relating a story about their brother Horatio Magruder., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 24 February 1861, Henry Minor Magruder, Glenmore in Albemarle County, Virginia, to John Bowie Magruder discussing family news, especially brother Horatio, and commenting on the crops in the county., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 28 February 1861, John Bowie Magruder to Henry Minor Magruder stating that he has had a bad cold which caused him to miss a party. John adds that he misses his brother and comments on other family news., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 9 March 1862, from John Bowie Magruder, Fort Dillard, [Gates County], North Carolina, to Evy [Eveline] M. Magruder describing the fort and the surrounding countryside. He states that his slave accidentally shot himself in the leg and needs someone to take his place until he recovers., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 29 April 1862, from John Bowie Magruder, Fort Dillard, to Henry Minor Magruder asking Henry to take care of a business matter for a friend of theirs. John adds that he is in command of Fort Dillard and the two companies stationed there., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 18 May 1862, John Bowie Magruder, near Petersburg, Virginia, to his father Benjamin Henry Magruder, Albemarle County, describing his regiment's march from Fort Dillard to Petersburg, including the fate of laggards, and mentioning the election of company and regimental officers., 10 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 8 June 1862, from John Bowie Magruder, near Drewery's Bluff, Virginia, to Henry Minor Magruder discussing business affairs, speculating on a Confederate invasion of the Union, and adding he has sent his company's extra baggage to Henry to be sent to soldiers' families., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 28 and 29 July 1862, from Henry Minor Magruder, Union Mills, [Fluvanna County], Virginia, to John Bowie Magruder discussing the visit of a cousin to Uncle Horatio's store in Fluvanna County, his health, and being a conscript., 8 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 9 December 1862, from John Bowie Magurder, near Fredericksburg, Virginia, to Henry Minor Magruder discussing business matters and family matters. He comments on life in camp and hopes his regiment will do well in battle., 6 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 20 December 1862, from John Bowie Magruder, near Fredericksburg, to his father Benjamin Henry Magruder commenting on how officers are selected, describing the battle of Fredericksburg, and remarking on members of his regiment., 8 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 2 January 1863, from John Bowie Magruder to Henry Minor Magruder providing news of his regiment and advising Henry on education, encouraging him to attend school., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 22 March 1863, Henry Magruder to John Bowie Magruder discussing personal and family news and asking how things are going for John., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 7 April 1863, from John Bowie Magruder to Henry Minor Magruder commenting on the military situation around Suffolk, Virginia, plans on an invasion of Maryland or Pennsylvania in the summer, and offering advice on Henry's education., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 23 May 1863, from John Bowie Magruder to Henry Minor Magruder describing the prices of items and services in Richmond, Virginia, and discussing Henry romantic escapades., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 27 May 1863, from John Bowie Magruder to his sister Julia Magruder Tyler describing his command's fight around Suffolk, his return to Richmond and meeting with friends, and his statement that the Army of Northern Virginia would invade Pennsylvania., 4 leaves, incomplete, negative photostats.
- Biographical sketches, n.d., of E. J. Magruder, George Shelton Magruder, John Hillary Magruder, James Watson Magruder, and E. T. H. Warren, all soldiers during the Civil War., 9 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter fragment, n.d., from John Bowie Magruder to [Henry Minor Magruder?] containing general news., 2 leaves, incomplete, negative photostats.